A Guide to the John Randolph Letters, 1806-1832
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John Randolph Letters, 1806-1832
Library of Virginia
19828
31 leaves, negative photostats
John Randolph
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Mrs. Charles Morton, Clarksville, Virginia, 20 November 1926.
Biographical Information
John Randolph of Roanoke was born 2 June 1773 in Prince George County, Virginia and settled in Charlotte County, Virginia. A member of the prominent Randolph family, he was cousins with Thomas Jefferson and John Marshall. Randolph served in the United States House of Representatives from 1799 to 1813, 1815 to 1817, 1819 to 1825, 1827 to 1829, and 1833, and in the United States Senate from 1825 to 1827. Randolph was an adherent of states' rights and the strict construction of the federal Constitution. He died in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 24 May 1833, freeing his slaves in his will. Randolph was buried at his home in Charlotte County, and later reinterred in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Letters, 1806-1832, of John Randolph (1773-1833) of Roanoke consisting of correspondence to his nephew John St. George Randolph at school in England and at home in Cumberland County, Virginia; Congressman Joseph Bryan of Georgia; Congressman Richard Stanford of North Carolina; William Leigh of Halifax County, Virginia; John Randolph Clay, charge d'affaires at the Russian Court; and "Mr. Ashby," overseer at Stoneleigh in Halifax County. Also contains a letter from George McDuffie of South Carolina to Randolph. Letters, 1806 and 1811, to his nephew John St. George Randolph concern his education at a school in England for deaf students, and John St. George Randolph's stay at Bizarre in Cumberland County, and provide family, local, and political news. Letter, 29 March 1808, to Joseph Bryan discusses relations between the United States and Great Britain. Letter, 23 December 1814, to Richard Stanford contains general news. Letters, 1822, 1828, and 1831, to William Leigh discuss Randolph's travels in England in 1822, his instructions to Leigh regarding his plantation in 1828, and his ocean voyage from England to the United States in 1831. Letters, 1831, to John Randolph Clay give Clay instructions while serving as United States charge d'affaires at the Russian Court in St. Petersburg, Russia. Letter, 17 September 1832, to (Benjamin) Watkins Leigh or his overseer Mr. Ashby concerns a slave Randolph has sent for work at Leigh's plantation. Letter, 28 February 1822, from George McDuffie to Randolph states that comments made in remarks by McDuffie were meant for Randolph and if were insulting, "they were such as the occasion demanded."
LVA accessions 19829, 19830, 19831, 19832, 19833, 19834, 19835, 19836, 19837, 19838, 19839, and 19840 are filed with accession 19828
Contents List
- Letter, 3 July 1806, John Randolph, Bizarre, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to John St. George Randolph, Hackney, near London, [England], sending him family and political news and offering advice on his education., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 6 September 1806, John Randolph, Bizarre, [Cumberland County], to John St. George Randolph, Hackney, near London, sending him family and political news and commenting on his education at a school for deaf students., 8 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 29 March 1808, John Randolph to Joseph Bryan [of Georgia] concerning relations between the United States and Great Britain., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 29 July 1811, John Randolph, Colonel Clarke's, Halifax [County, Virginia], to John St. George Randolph, Bizarre, [Cumberland County], inviting to continue at Bizarre., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 4 November 1811, John Randolph, [Washington], to John St. George Randolph, Bizarre, [Cumberland County], containing family and political news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 23 December 1814, John Randolph, York Buildings [?], to Richard Stanford [of North Carolina], Washington, containing personal news., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 22 June 1822, John Randolph, London, to William Leigh, Halifax Court House, [Virginia], describing Randolph's stay in London., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 30 December 1828, John Randolph to William Leigh providing instructions for Randolph's plantation., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 23 November 1830, John Randolph, London, to John Randolph Clay, [St. Petersburg, Russia], sending Clay news and providing Clay with advice on how to handle the United States ministry in Russia., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 23 November 1830, John Randolph, London, to John Randolph Clay, St. Petersburg, Russia, sending advice on how to handle the U.S. ministry in Russia., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 13 October 1831, John Randolph, New York, to [William?] Leigh commenting on Randolph's ocean voyage from London to New York., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 17 September 1832, John Randolph to [Benjamin?] Watkins Leigh or "Mr. Ashby, the overseer at Stoneleigh, Halifax County noting that he is sending Davy to work for Ashby., 1 leaf, negative photostats.
- Letter, 28 February 1822, George McDuffie, [Washington], to John Randolph, [Washington], concerning remarks McDuffie made about Randolph during a debate in Congress., 1 leaf, negative photostats.